hello everybody thanks for tuning in to
this conversation with john riveicky
today
i'll set some context for that in a
moment but for some housekeeping
um we have just opened a registration
for the first
online art of circling course
links for that below it's it's a
year-long training in the art of
facilitating circling
if you want to know what more about
circling you could both
look at the links below and i also just
released a video
the last video before this um of me
doing a demo a demo circle with uh an
artist circling group so you'll get it
you can get a chance in that video
to see this you know the kind of the set
setting setting and what it's like and
what circling is and
um and so it's rare in that circling
very difficult to capture um
through video in my experience but this
one really does a good job and it gets
to the front of the
other so go ahead and check that out and
also if you're interested in
one-on-one coaching with me uh
go ahead and email me the emails below
all right this is uh my ongoing uh
dialogue
with my my friend john vervecki john
is a cognitive scientist
and philosopher and professor at the
university of toronto
um we've been talking we met about eight
months ago or so
and uh through
through the interactions with john in
our relationship
and all the relationships that have
spurred and interwoven with those
a lot of which a lot of the
conversations i've had
we've seen a lot of them um has
spurred and birds something that uh the
ancient
art of dialogues and
it's been revealing itself to us in so
many ways
uh it's something that's always been
present for me personally
however it's i'm seeing it more
and we're we're inventing and
discovering and shaping
it with more and more articulation of
language that reveals it
so um you can really feel the sense i
really felt my friendship with john
and our collaboration in this
on so many levels so enjoy
thank you
record hey john
it's so good to see you it's good to see
you there
good to see you man so good to see you
i'm enjoying your i'm enjoying your
aliveness
right i can feel your inspiration about
about in
like i can see i can feel what you're
facing right like what you're what
you're looking at and
how how they're talking to you because
they're it seems like it's calling you
almost out of here
[Laughter]
well like we were talking about just
before we hit before
there's there's so much happening right
now and there and
there's just so much uh there's so much
i'm being exposed to and learning about
that
um has so much real promise in it
um and for you know for the work we're
doing together
and for the kind of uh like i was
thinking about it the other day
because you know i i get some people who
criticize me or you you know you need to
move
me more political and blah blah and i
was thinking the other day i'm not after
the french revolution or the american
revolution of the russian revolution
i'm after something like the axial
revolution that's what i'm
uh that's what kind of revolutionary i
am yes right
and so i'm actually seeing like
we were talking we can get into a little
bit later yeah the discord server
networks and
some of the the a lot of the other
people like there's this converging
thing happening
um i i i'm just seeing a lot of that
especially in this time of kairos right
i'm just seeing
so much so much potential i'm so excited
it's it's a weird place guy because um
i've been telling people this and i i
still don't know what the proper affect
for
what i'm gonna say is and i keep trying
it on and nothing feels quite right but
um you know the kovic
crisis has really um increased the
relevancy of my work that's what people
are telling me right uh and you know
chris
and andrew and i have been talking about
how it's
you know it's done these two things that
you need both of these for a kairos
right
for a lot of people it's really
exacerbated domicide it's really
accelerated a lot of the features
crisis uh but for other people it's
shifted their attention right into the
being mode
right and then there's two things there
that are happening
one you know it came out with the
discussion with johannes he was sort of
prescient about this
that people are throwing back under the
subjectivity only to find how shallow
yeah he is in a lot of ways and so
there's that
in their bubbling and then there's
people who are rediscovering
this rediscovering what weight
weight you know a lot of what really
matters is this ability to connect to
other people
yes and so i've i've been privileged uh
to just be i feel
i mean i feel called to it and there are
many people calling out to me about it
and so this has been just a really
intense time for me uh but
in a very good sense a very good sense
yes
that's amazing that's awesome and it's
going for you it's
it's i it's going really good um
i mean for me that the there's not a
whole lot
that i'm doing that's that much
different i mean i'm doing stuff with
the circling institute and you know
we're starting
we're starting all kinds of new stuff um
my wife is home which is really great
and we've got we brought everything
online which is you know i was pretty
hesitant on doing
um but like now that we've done it it
actually works
remarkably well yeah yeah and so i'm
culturating
yeah right totally so i'm having people
like
we're doing uh we just opened we just
opened
um enrollment for the first circling
training course online
um and so we're having people from all
over the world right
somebody just from norway just signed up
um that's
cool yeah so it's like it's really
interesting
but like when somebody's you know we
have the the circling nights on
on every thursday and and to have
all these people from you know from all
different time zones even different days
right australia and norway and russia
and
like show up right in our
are have a quality of interest that
that everyone kind of meets with this
kind of quality of interest or
something's been
shining forth to them maybe you don't
even have words for it
however that this medium
allows everybody to actually find each
other which is
amazing i mean it's kind of like just
think about it's like what
how would we have ever met right yeah if
it wasn't for this
we've yet to meet in person yeah yeah
absolutely
um so so yeah i think it's
i this this time for me has been
is it's just it's well one thing is i've
also just moved to
alameda which is like a little island
right right by san francisco
and and i've just been able to just i've
gone on tons of walks and i live in this
old historical neighborhood
and and as i'm walking along there's uh
alameda is one of those places that you
can you can't get it
just by going to it once like it reveals
itself to you and i'm getting
and it's it's turning out to be the
perfect place for
brienne and i was like yeah
so it's like on one level for me
personally there's a there's a uh
there's like a simplicity and almost a
meditativeness
right like inwardly but outwardly
on all these other levels i'm like more
i'm reading more crazy stuff and like
meditating in these different ways and
doing all these experiments and
my you know i'm exploring
and pushing edges on uh on a pretty
profound level
that's great at the same time it's
really weird how this is
this is bifurcated right so i mean
some of us are very lucky privileged
you are i am that you know our lives
have
a particular structure to them that has
a resiliency to them
uh other people are not so fortunate
right
and both both physically
and psychologically they're being
hammered really really hard and i get to
talk to some of those people
um and trying to
reach out and provide some kind of
support and help for them
has been something i've been trying to
address as you know i've been doing a
free
online meditation and contemplation
class
a course and that
i'm getting the feedback i'm getting is
that people are finding it very helpful
very relevant and very helpful but i am
very cognizant of the fact
like i said that this is a very strange
time the system is being very radically
destabilized
and that always brings with tremendous
suffering and distress
but right you know but it also brings
both individually as you and i are
finding
but i think even more important
collectively as i think you
will both see it within this new this
new you know
this almost male strum of amazing
conversations and
community building that's occurring
right there's also it's a tremendous
opportunity
for people too um and so
i feel for both of those reasons
for both of them together almost like
stereoscopic vision
i feel a tremendous urgency right now
there's a tremendous urgency right now
oh yeah totally yeah there is an urgency
and there's a way there's a way to
commune about it
right i can just get this sense that
there's there's
when i look at like the rebel wisdom
community
and i look at all the people watching
our videos and all
like the discord server all the things
that we're talking about
i just i'm like okay where
where were those people before all this
right like there's a there's a way where
there's a certain kind of
quality of conversation or um uh
an openness to a certain and what i like
about it it's a it's a mode that's
distinct for me because it's not
just like as i think you would talk
about it's not just
the embodiment authentic relating
right mode but it's um but it's
but it's also and it's not just the kind
of academic or intellectual
mode but they're it's it seems to be
attracting people who have a
have a sense for both of them right yes
and want to hang and like have a sense
of being
interested um and drawn to that
and yeah yeah yeah yeah they're not
academics
and they're not just into uh the
importance
because you know you know more than
anybody else and i've experienced
the importance of that kind of
interpersonal intimacy and
that word means a lot for me right the
interpersonal intimacy
you get in circling but these people
they're there
they're they're they're connoisseurs of
intelligibility
they right they they want a taste um
they want right and so yeah and and so
they're the people that you know i'm
trying
well we you know this is a group project
right
that we're trying to work i'm just
saying what i'm putting a lot of my work
into and i know you are too
this is what i'm trying to you know
craft
you know double vision looking back to
the best historical
templates we have looking at the current
cutting-edge emerging practices and
community practices
craft the psychotechnology of dialectic
to afford the logos so that people know
what it is like to taste by knowing
right you know you know the serious play
with intelligibility and what does that
mean
you know i'm not just as a cognitive
agent but what does it mean as an
existential being
that that's that's why that community
is the community that i'm especially
trying to reach
and so generally i find that people that
are sort of purely academically oriented
or purely theoretically oriented they
sort of go what's this
and you know where's the theory and i
say well i've got
lots of theory elsewhere this is this is
something else i'm trying to do here
yeah and the people that there's other
people you probably encounter this a lot
yeah well i just want to feel close to
other people right yes
but but you know we need more than that
right now right we need
more than that right now yeah we need a
lot more right now
um so yeah the the community
like the people that you are identifying
as
a population that's the people that i am
most
um because uh most concerned to help to
afford
to address uh and to listen to and to
listen to
right right absolutely and the the thing
that you've been talking about
lately i've heard you talk about lately
is these these two distinctions
are bringing together a couple of things
i wanted to
to highlight them and pin them because
it gets to what you wanted to talk about
in the beginning i think
which i want to circle back around to
which is
this way that of looking at right this
that where where the two you could say
bottom up and top down right kind of
meet and bleed into each other and point
to each other right
this sense of this sense of um
like being with like being with somebody
and their suchness
yes yeah right
and in the same time there's there's in
dialogues there's there's reaching
into and being reached by the
inexhaustible
right the beyondness the the moreness
right and it's in when you when you when
you put it like that
right um it's interesting because i
thought
i had a felt sense of exactly
i thought that was the the perfect two
things to bring it together in that way
because i've noticed this sense
and what in fact i just uploaded a
circle i did
um a training circle i did um onto my
channel which was
kind of watching going deep into this
getting
getting this person's essence right
but it it just bled into these kind of
really big insights right and
and they were it was almost like you
could talk about the most
like difficult personal thing for
her and what's opening up around that to
like the nature of the universe at the
same time
it's like at some point they just like
they became figure ground and then they
just started to bleed into each other
blake i think that's exactly right um
and um i think you're alluding to the
conversation i had with paul vander clay
about this and um so i was
you know i'm not i'm not very happy with
like sorry
with uh the term but i don't
and you know some of the people on the
discord server were saying could you get
it come up with a better term but
i mean it was circled around this idea
that i was playing with a trying
serious play with or trying to give a
secular version of
soul because i want to
one of the things that i'm really
working on right now is i'm
going to be talking about rebel wisdom
i'm trying to break out of the three
monos
uh the idea you know that the the mind
is monolithic it has one way of knowing
propositional knowing
right uh the idea that the mind is
ultimately monologic
and that reason is monologic rather than
what all the accumulating evidence
and practice is showing no it's
ultimately dialogical with nature right
and then the mind is monophasic there's
one state of consciousness you should be
in and only that state of consciousness
gives access to reality and all the
other ones are just aberrant i'm trying
to break
out of all of that in a significant
fashion and so
what descartes did was he tied the
notion of soul
and self you first of all fuse them
together i mean they
tied that to that that you know that
inner point of subjectivity
that is the center of the monolith that
that triple model mind
that three dimensions of being sort of
monolithic monophasic
right mono monologic and i'm trying i'm
thinking
well what if we
what if we try to re so there's this
wonderful word that uh
carrie uses is in his book on augustine
and the uh the invention of the inner
self he says that what he actually wants
is the latin word inventio
which means both to discover and to
invent yeah so things that we
see as dichotomous yeah think about how
relevant that is to deal logos saying
because you're both discovering and
inventing right
right right i said to paul i wanted to
try and reinvent your soul
to break out of that right that triple
monism
right of mine of mine yeah and i wanted
to redo it in terms of its phenomenology
and functionality and that's what i was
trying to get at
yeah oh i was trying to get at something
like
analogous geez i hope i'm not offending
people i really don't want you paul
didn't take offense
something analogous to worship like what
reverence is because this is part of
what
you and i are talking about with the
deal logos right the reference for the
logos when it emerges
and i was trying to get out okay well
the soul was though
was the faculty of worship what does
that mean well
normally that means just sort of
praising and stating things but i
thought
well where what if what if right
what if it was it's the faculty that
mediates
between the mourners and the suchness
yeah right your soul
is that which right so your spirit is
that which
affords you self-transcendence but your
soul
is that is the locust right it's the
horizon of intelligibility the genus
space thing
that is simultaneously synoptically
right like stereoscopic vision like
symbolon joining together
it's with seeing together symbol on
together
the moreness and the suchness that's the
soul and then just like you were saying
yeah you picked up on this perfectly you
know i've been talking to chris about
you know that the soulful nature
of the logos right that what happens is
you get
if the if the if the logos is present
you get a sense simultaneously of
the moreness of participation
but the suchness of individuation and
their those two mysteries
are just resonating with each other and
there's this there's this
faculty that comes in into awareness
yeah so i'm trying to reinvent you right
so the the you know there's something
soulful
about uh you know dialogos
and and what it does is it picks up on
our that part of us that is the
active symbol between the mourners and
the sections
paul actually really liked that as sort
of a secular version
of that um yeah so i'm just trying to i
mean
if you see you know what i'm doing of
course i'm trying to bring as much of
the theater
in the theory right as possible
right so that that that thing you just
said sorry it was so pregnant i had to
unpack it a lot
totally yeah there's so much going on
midwife
there's so much going on there because
like because
you know it picks up on you know what
what christopher and i are talking about
in the chapter you know that
the sensibility transcendence is really
picking up on the suchness of another
person
and the anagadi is picking up on the
mourners but you
every participant is soulful in that
they
are they are the symbol on right the
stereoscopic
fusion and symbology
and that's part of the phenomenology and
the functionality of being in via logos
right right yeah yeah totally
and there's this is to remember satie
anamnesis
this is to remember the soul and yet to
break out of the cartesian
monism right that that that the monism
of mind
monolithic you know monophasic
monological mind and yeah say no no
mind is well let's reserve mine for
problem solving and cognition
soul is this existential mediating
function
yeah totally and this in this
you know bringing it bringing that back
into just you know i'm taking all this
and i'm just bringing this back into
this sense of what you're talking about
which is
this this um help me out with this but
the what you were talking about this
this sense of of
of speaking or or thinking oh
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
so i mean when people sometimes ask me
to give them the elevator pitch for
dialectic
so dialectic is the psycho technology
deal logos is the process you
participate in
right so you have to do dialectic but
you can only participate
in via logo right right very similar to
the distinction between dialectic and
dialogue
right yeah the book that you and i are
both reading um
so but the the the the
one of so the elevator pitch i give to
people is uh
you've realized the logos when you're
both
getting to a place that neither one of
you could have gotten to
on on your own right and so that and
people
people have an intuitive sense of what
that means so it's great for practicing
yeah yeah i sort of know what that means
and then how do i get there and then
that
that that's a really good opening it's a
good elevator pitch
yes but then i was thinking i was
thinking okay but let's get a little bit
more fine-grained let's you know
let's let's you know a finer resolution
and i was thinking about
well part of what that means not
comprehensively but part of what it
means
is i've been noticing that when i'm
practicing it
with you guys with other people that i'm
doing this weird thing
normally you know people
think and then they speak right and then
they listen and then they
think right and there's a little bit of
online yeah
but there's something different when
i start practicing dialectic and via
logos starts to
project yeah which is i find that
i'm thinking by speaking and by thinking
right
speaking yeah so that's like i'm trying
to get there's a felt
sense and a felt difference in
functionality
between being monolith being monological
just talking in your head
and then when i put it out and i'm
speaking to you and i'm getting your
online feedback
even gesturally and you know intuitively
and implicit learning
then what happens is right i'm noticing
that the
act of articulating my words
in your presence is actually
you know it's it's it's articulating in
in the sense of action
it's articulating my thinking my
thinking is coming into shape
as i'm speaking right like i can't
tell you what my thought is going to be
yeah until the speaking has has sort of
finished a cycle of resonance with yeah
yeah
yeah oh interesting
and so that reminded me of something and
you and i talked about this before i
tried to think about
where else have i felt that kind of
thing and it reminded me of
when teaching is going well
i'm learning as i'm teaching right and
i'm
itching because i'm learning because i'm
teaching yes
my learning isn't done and then i'm
teaching and i'm not just learning
i'm simultaneously teaching and learning
as i'm teaching like
the active teaching is opening things
up yeah yeah there's the teaching
and the learning are happening in this
completely parallel and interpenetrating
fashion
yes that's not just an analogy
or a similarity because in the figure of
socrates
both of those are happening like the
thinking by speaking and the teaching by
learning
are also like this yes
right right right totally and this
there's also this sense in which
yeah i mean i'm just fee i'm seeing
visually all the
you know the normativity right that is
uh that that that's that's being
that's being this you know using your
hands and me too that like hands back
and forth like this sense of like
finding each other right co-finding each
other shaping each other
and and in that as that normativity
starts to catch hold
right you start to break into you start
saying stuff that you didn't know about
yes right exactly like but it but it's
but it's
wedded in some way to the other person's
listening
in that particular way where it's like
the speaking
it's almost like it's almost like it's
as if
it's as if you know
my my words are more like the thought
and the other person is more like the
the the the representation of that
thought
like realizing itself back around
right yeah that's that's very well said
yeah that's very well said
because there is that partner there is
that part of listening
which is really interesting to think
about listening like this relationship
between listening and thought
right because did you get this book i
think it went
and one of my students recommended it to
me yeah
right i'm just about to start it
oh yeah totally yeah i've read that like
five ten times
yeah so i i i saw that's a really good
book
that's a really good book yeah but
one of the things that she actually goes
into a lot is that
well she talks about how
and this is what had me start thinking
about it is how listening is really
we think about listening usually like
being an empty vessel
and sound comes in and we receive this
now that's not it at all
no it's synonymous with interpretation
and in some way right when you
talk and i listen if i'm listening
right and i start thinking is the moment
i stop listening
right and that what that i think that
shows is shows how wedded
listening and thinking really are
together yeah right
so i think of listening more and more
like
you know uh like the internalization
that is needed for genuine sensibility
transcendence
in john writes like all right this is
this is again
right part of when i'm listening what
i'm doing is trying to
tailor my attention my memory my
receptivity to your suchness yeah
right so like i i feel like oh here's
the suchness and then behind me
and behind you sort of around us all
right is is the moreness yeah right and
so
right i try to speak the moreness and i
try to listen to your suchness
does that make any sense but yeah yeah
yeah yeah that that that's that's
that's the moreness and i listen to your
suchness yeah
yes yeah exactly exactly
exactly it's almost like where my
it's like in some way
like right now i'm kind of i i can hear
it i'm like listening for what's being
thought
yes yes and then and then you said yes
yes
exactly right so there's that sense in
which there's that sense in which
i i listen for what and then i speak it
right
and then and then you respond in that
sense
and there's something that like what's
the feat like then then then that goes
back over here what does that do
right so and i'm wondering about if
that's kind of the normativity or the
the sense of honing into the sweet spot
like
feeling into oh and here's that thing
about like okay
that sense in which i've noticed this
too of where you're
you're you're listening to somebody and
then
something happens and you it it breaks
the flow
and it and it's agitating right
but i didn't know like i didn't know
that there was a flow i was
tuned into until it broke right right
right
so there's that sense of like that sense
of like on some level
we both are finding out what we're
tuning into
right and that seems to be
that sense of like is that what you and
chris have been talking about the geist
right yeah the guy's the third factor
yeah i think
i think the geist is the soul
of the logos the way right
so what what you're getting is like
so it reminds me of fisher's notion of
wonder and wonder is you're on the
horizon of intelligibility
and what the logos is the logos is right
it's the
it's it's the presence of the horizon of
intelligibility it's the moreness
of intelligibility shining through the
suchness of what's
particularly spoken in in a
non-repeatable fashion right if we try
to make this in any way formulaic
we'll lose it yeah lose it it always has
to be jazz right it always has to be
jazz
and i was trying to you know what i was
trying to think about okay
well again what's that doing
well we are we're not just talking about
the logos yeah we're
embodying it we're instantiating it
and but then we're also right we're also
it is also symbol on it's also finding
us
you know the way br being is disclosing
itself
as i keep saying you know the deal logos
defines us to the onto logos
yeah and and so
for me that moment of the third factor
like you said that where where i mean
part of it is
you know part of it is you know
cognitive science part of it is
what's happening is you and i are
figuring out right how to get into the
zone of proximal development
you're putting enough challenge on me
that i have to stay really engaged
yeah like if i if i start to break out
of authenticity
you start to give me error signal really
rapidly even by like
your brows will go down slightly yeah
so we're doing all the flow stuff but
we're doing more than that right because
there's also this
there's and this is this is what i'm
trying to talk we're trying to
right we're trying to
we're trying to give birth all right
it's it's a deeper conception of consent
of conception
right we're trying to give birth like
that this flow itself
isn't that's that's not the goal the
flow is
it's great but the flow is ultimately
the affordance of
a reorientation of faith coming into
right relationship with other people
right relationship with ourselves right
relationship with being
that's what this is ultimately about
right totally
coming into right relationship yes like
this cop it's both a reveal
yeah it's a revealing right and
a coming to being revealed it's it's
it's exactly what i like about that it's
like almost it's almost like
un-dogmatizable
exactly and that and so you know
corresponding to trying to reinvent your
soul and to reinvent your faith in terms
of this sense of faithfulness and you
know jordan and i have been talking a
lot about this jordan hall and i
i can think about how you're faithful to
brianna it doesn't mean that you have a
fuck you don't have a set of dogmas you
don't have i now have you
in it i have my set of unchangeable
beliefs about you
right that's not what it means in fact
that's that's that's disaster
if you get it it means i am i have
coupled the emergence of me
to the emergence of you so that those
will always
be affording and constraining each other
and so
that's faithfulness right yeah that's
that's
faithfulness and so that's that's that
continuity of contact
yes that cognitive contact right a
so thinking about right relationship as
evolving
adaptive continuity of contact
not as you said as any closure or
dogmatization
right right right
you know i'm cut i'm i've been i've been
by the way i really have enjoyed
the psychologist that you've had on a
couple of times i think he's also
yeah oh yeah that last that last one
yeah that last one where he laid out he
brought up the picture and laid out the
the model the justification the
justified yeah
that so so
there's something about this thing about
being a forum
right like the world be of being a forum
in which i
i am on trial right on some level
for justification right
so i i want to just kind of like think
about this right
but that's so socratic right that that
that what we're doing
that we and this this is what
christopher moore argues so brilliantly
and he's
his book and you see it also in
gonzalo's book right yeah that
we we only really
know ourselves as persons when we enter
the field of justification yeah right
which is not the field of blame it's not
the field of accusation
this is how we mess these things up it's
a field of justification
and that you know greg on reeks and i
are i'm going to have him on regularly
like once a month
on voices with raviki i really want you
to talk to him right
i think it'd be really amazing yeah but
but moore's idea right
that i only it's i only
it's not introspection it's not even
reflection
it's not going over my autobiography how
i know myself as a person is only
seeing how i enter into and commit
myself within the arena of justification
so self-examination and the examination
of the ways of life to which i'm willing
to commit myself
yes and how they are affined to the ways
of speaking to which i'm willing to
commit myself
that's the only way of knowing yourself
as a person yeah
yeah absolutely yeah absolutely yeah i
mean
i thought i've thought about this a
bunch of times if like if you took an
infant you're right you put it on a
desert
like an island and it just grew up like
what would it
say it could speak right which you
couldn't but like what when you asked it
about itself what would it say
it reminds me of wittgenstein's things
even if lions could speak we wouldn't
understand them yeah
it would be this would be this would be
a biological human being presumably
linguistic in some fashion but
i mean i i say this really carefully and
i don't want to fall
into some sort of easy moral error or be
subject to
unreasonable moral judgment but i don't
it wouldn't speak as a person
yeah speak as a person because it hasn't
had to
it hasn't had to take response this
isn't gonna work
as it had to take responsibility for
you know tending the logos yes yes
so there's something about so there's
something about right if we look at like
the logos and the conditions of
dialogues right
um
like at one level what we're talking
about is like the va
it's like what you're what you're saying
is is the very stuff of which our
development develops through
right it's like it's on some level it's
like this is
some of this stuff is just site this is
like developmental psychology in a lot
in a lot of ways however
i think the thing that were
for whatever reason right this kind of
sense about what's
possible in relating this way as a
spiritual practice
right has not really i've not seen it
right
i've not seen it in the set in the way
that we're talking about i think that
there was like
there's this you know the platonic
dialogues
right but the you know most of that is
just
i mean most of that stuff has just been
studied you know systematized and
studied and
yeah in academic settings but the sense
of
and i just i wonder too what you think
about this blind spot
where when um gonzalez starts to talk
about
like no you gotta you can't just
interpret
the content of the dialogue you gotta
like look at the
it's the process itself is
is is is kind of in so many ways is is
is the place where you find out where
the thing really is
it's the point of the dialogues yeah
that's what gonzalez argues
argues yeah moore argues like this is
this isn't like this is
played like you and i pay attention i'm
saying to listeners pay attention
there's this growing convergence about
you know how much
the drama is doing as much work
as the arguments yeah within the
platonic dialogue
all of that very very much right in fact
in fact oftentimes the arguments are
just bring you to the supporia
where all of a sudden none of the
answers right that that classic
right ironic like socratic thing is
where everything just falls apart
and then and then then everyone's really
like ecstatic
right at the end and and people and
gonzales points out that
but what you get is you get the people
who are often
the combative interlocutors with
socrates but i want my sons to come and
spend time with you
because again a way of life a right
relationship
to the logos of intelligibility has been
disclosed to them and they have an
intuitive sense
that being around somebody who can
regularly bring this practice about
is going to be beneficial to their kids
in a way in which
you know the the over technicalization
of
the sofas and yes the the the
obviousness of common sense
won't educate because think about what
you've said a few minutes ago
you know this stuff we're talking about
here this is the guts
of personhood spirituality and reverence
are about
you know accessing and activating and
celebrating and accelerating
personhood i mean that's that's what
it's about yes um
so it got me thinking about also what
you just said a minute ago sorry there's
you're setting up firecrackers in my
mind right but fireworks
about the normativity and i was thinking
that when we want to turn
this because we're doing it all
naturally
but i'm trying to think about okay but
to teach to
model yeah i i thought you know i don't
think it's happenstance
that the dialogues are about virtues
yeah because virtue is the place where
the moreness
and the suchness where the
intelligibility and the normativity
are coming together it's like that's the
top
because it's both yes by its very nature
it has to be shareable with others
but it has to be personally relevant to
you within your with your ability as a
person
to commit yourself to to the forum of
justification
right the logos brings together
intelligibility and commitment
so the main topics of philosophia should
be the virtues it should be like
what is love but i'm going to expand the
virtues what is meaning
what is wonder what is beauty like all
of these
that's like like so it's not going to be
like pure philosophy we're going to talk
about the nature of cause
or blah blah blah blah but it's going to
be it's good there is it's not
happenstance that the topics are the
virtues
and this is where your intuition about
how lecto d like if you do lecture
divina in a group right will
will kind of naturally kind of just give
rise most likely to dialogue
right yeah because i mean so
if readers want to see this they can go
to my channel um
and the lesson i gave yesterday on how
to practice lecture divina
it should not be practiced until it's an
advanced technique
you should go through you should have at
least an introductory course
meditation contemplation before you
practice lectio but
uh let's take that for granted yeah i
think the point about lexio as a
as a bridging practice is because on one
side it reaches into the propositions
because you're reading
but yeah but like part of the lectio is
you set yourself to listen
right you recite it yeah and you set
yourself with an intention
to resonate with it and to read for
transformation not to read for
information
yeah so you recite and you resonate and
then you
you you're open to what grabs your
attention yeah and then you internalize
it and then you enact it
vaginally not in your imagination space
introspectively
you like projectively on the world and
then what would it be like to live
this way right what would you like to
actually commit myself to this
sort of an existential ethic then what's
disclosed
about being if i were to live this way
and correspondingly here's the
normativity what would be demanded from
me
in order to come into conformity with
that realization
yeah and then the idea is you know what
so i'm teaching people
how to do it individually but on the
discord server we're talking about yeah
but we want to do this continually and
that's so so important right yeah yeah
so what i see it happening is one person
would do the rest citation
and then everybody has their own
individual moments where they're doing
going through this process alexia divina
yeah but then they start to share
all the different perspectival and
participatory transformations
that are that they're getting an inkling
of that they are getting a taste
connoisseur of how to aspire and then i
think that will naturally start to lead
into right into the logos because
you know that the sacred prose the
sacred poetry and the sacred prose
you should read both by the way one of
each because you want you want them to
talk to each other so that they can talk
to you
right right um but that that
right that's gonna naturally that you're
gonna you're gonna get
the dylexio is gonna reach back because
you do it after you've done a meditative
or contemplative practice or a priority
practice non-duality practice it's gonna
reach back to that
that's gonna afford you resonating with
the propositions but moving into the
perspective of participatory
right and then it's gonna when you're
doing it in group it's gonna naturally
feed
into the logos because right what you're
training
is a really the virtue that is
needed for aspiration right and
transformation which is the virtue of
reverence
paul woodruff's idea that reverence
reverence is a particular kind of
relevance realization
yeah that properly puts you into right
relationship
to what awe and wonder disclose to you
as possible
yeah in fact i'm wondering about like so
now i'm i'm just flashing back to like
all the moments that were like that
like body memory but like things and so
like some of the most immediate ones
right are it has to be wonder
is the is the thing that is becomes
present and we in a certain sense see
right when this when the suchness and
the moreness
like are you know we're foreground
they've once they become foreground
becca and they do this
switching at some point they bleed into
each other where it's just animating
yeah i'm wondering is like it's kind of
like when i think about that sense of
being deeply moved by somebody
right yes that sense of being in
reverence right like disc like
i'm disclosed in there in disclosing
them
right and that there's that sense of
like re reverence where their
um their suchness is just a lie
i think it's usually i'm wondering about
on another
level if that's like almost like we're
in the direct
um to the the the virtue
that i'm actually seeing a virtue in you
right
that is um that in some way is
is like the i don't know if there was an
s like if there was an essential
if it was a sound right like is that is
that the the sense of where the the
virtue
where the the the suchness and the
moreness meet is that's the point where
the virtue the sound of the virtue goes
i think that's exactly right you know
and so murdoch
talks about this in the sovereignty of
the good
and that's where john wright got the
notion of sensibility transcendence
from uh so when when those two like
the virtue i think is the ver i think
the virtue
i would say this this is how she says it
i'm now
seeing you in a virtuous manner she says
that the the primary
act of virtue of ethics is proper
attention
attending to things justly is the core
um any that that's the core
virtuous act for her right because if
that that's where that's that's that's
where that's that
nexus point you're pointing to and i
think attending to things
justly is a part
of what reverence means right
again this is the secular overlap with
what
worship used to mean worship didn't used
to mean being sort of a syncophanic
toady to god
and i don't mean anything insulting to
the people that i know who i think
you know but but i'm talking about a
caricature that has become prevalent in
popular culture
yeah monkey python has made fun of it
like in the meaning of life
right oh god you're so really big don't
burn us you know all that all that kind
of crap
right but what i think was what what was
going on in what i guess for lack of a
better term i don't like this adjective
but
authentic worship right what was exactly
that is the sense of
you know there is a just attention
that carries with that i should have to
god and that brings with it a sense of
reverence that i i
enter into the virtue of maintaining
the right relationship with that which
continually can be a
found of intelligibility for me through
awe and wonder
right that's that's what i'm trying to
unpack here
yeah yeah absolutely
and there's that that sense in which the
virtue
in which i'm seeing let's say like let's
just say i
see something about you and your life
right in that moment and something
shine for and just moves me yes yes
and yeah we talked about that remember
the symposium he says you move from
and we've talked about this the beauty
right you move from the physical beauty
right to the beauty of virtue right
right yes
and exactly that so i i think that's
exactly right when that and that that
moment sort of crystallizes
right and there's that and it's fun
it's really interesting because at those
moments
i noticed that the
that it's so there is a silence that's
so much at ease in
in in in partaking right
because i think that's where the theory
of theory like
we talked about this because what
happens when you're talking about virtue
right
people are like they're they're what
they're doing is they move
from reflecting to participating in its
exemplification
yeah yeah you and i what you think about
how
you and i are doing this i know you're
doing it i'm doing it right
we're we're trying to notice in what
we're doing the very virtue
that we're also talking about this is
what i mean by thinking
and by speaking the speaking right is
sort of you know what you're doing is
you're constantly moving between
reflection
right and exemplification that's why
that's why i can't
think independently of speaking it the
speaking is where i engage
in the mirroring of the exemplification
right right
right when we when we connect it's like
ah and so i can continually go back and
forth between
right and this is what you should be
doing in good phenomenology right
back and forth between here's my
conceptualization here's my articulation
here's my attempt to speak the
intelligibility of the logos
but here is my connectedness here's my
participant
here's my participation in
exemplification right of the very thing
and virtues do that for us
virtue is the topic that not only
commits us to aspiration
it also constantly toggles us between
speech
reflective speech and speech that
exemplifies and enacts
right totally oh interesting it's like
it's interesting because the virtues
themselves
right if it's it makes sense to call it
themselves right
yeah it seems like virtues are those
things
that like it's a little bit they they're
starting to occur to me a little bit
like
light you know how light has it it it
it withdrawals in its complete
disclosure right
that's it that's the whole point about
you know the virtues and
and plato makes very clear and uh
highland makes this really clear in the
question of beauty
that things like beauty should be your
ability to relate to beauty properly
should be considered a via virtue as
well
right but but but think about think
about what what what constantly happens
as you pointed out in the dialogues
we can't get a definition of courage
what we can get
is an ongoing right relationship to it
not just in thought
and reflection but because we're
exemplifying it
it's also calling us to commitment it's
calling us to the space of justification
right it's calling us to transformation
we can't get a definition
but we can't rely on just our untutored
intuitions about courage either
you have to enter into this process and
all we get
is an ongoing right relationship virtues
are
also the thing that steer us between
definition and into
an untutored intuition totally it's
almost like there's
a sense of getting a sense of it like
tuning an instrument like to picture it
right
it's a tone us yeah yes and then you've
got to say that guy you have to say that
you're you're heidegger incarnate here
right
right and the attunement right yeah but
for the longest
time you know i hope for when i first
read that i only got it sort of
conceptually
yeah and then i sort of got it
phenomenologically but now
and i hope this is the right adjective
yeah i'm getting it spiritually i'm
getting what that attunement yeah
oh it's bound up with total soulfulness
and faithfulness
and and virtue in the way we're talking
about here right
totally well it's interesting like when
you think about attunement
it's it's that thing where it's it's
interesting a tuning is one of those
things where it's like
you it's it's kind of a little bit like
you know acquaintance talks about time
right you know
if you don't ask me i know exactly what
time is right
so the moment you ask me i realize it's
i have no fuck i have no idea it's i'm
personally perplexed right
there's a sense with the two met that
it's kind of like that like if you don't
ask me what attunement is
i know exactly what it is because it's
but there's something about when you go
what is attunement
but there is this quality of like i was
thinking about this like with
the the the sense of right is thinking
about
about tears and grief right
and and like oftentimes what i see is
is that when someone's in grief right
for example it's like
and they're alone there's a way in which
it's not
totally grief until they speak about it
and in pert right i've got to tell you
about something yeah please
so um
i i i want i want it i want to slow down
because i want to treat this with proper
reverence
but there was i was doing a a a
one of the like the live classes
and somebody brought up and i won't
disclose their name because i want to
trespass on privacy but i do want to i
do want to express
yeah you know um
gratitude for their honesty their
courage they brought up that they were
in grief and they were asking well
how can the practice help and
part of what i i tried to articulate is
how grief has to be shared not because
there's a solution grief is a permanent
deporia
right to use our language here but what
we're after
is the way in which grief deeply
humanizes
is in the sense of puts us into that
soulful faithfulness
right because i was talking about i i
related the story of
well i'll quickly do it here because i
think it's helpful
so a woman comes to the buddha and her
son has died
this is this is i love this
one of those things that like moved me
oh yeah and she says to the buddha
you know resurrect him because i i love
my son i'm in such deep greeting
and she and she's he says no because he
he always refused to do miracles right
and she keeps asking and she's
persistent so then he turns her and says
okay i will do it but first you have to
do one thing
you have to go into the city and you
have to go to a household
and find a household where there's a
mustard seed oh great that's easy
wait one thing it has to be that nobody
in that household has tasted death or
grief
yeah right so she goes and she knocks on
the door and
do you have any mustard seed just one oh
yeah sure but oh but has anybody tasted
death oh yes of course
and then she goes from house to house
to house to house
and then she goes oh and then she comes
back to the buddha and she says
thank you now i get it now i get it
right and then i said that what we what
we need
is we there's no answer the whole
proposition
what we need is we need to felt that
we're that we need to felt seen
i thought about you when i was saying
that we need to help we need to feel
seen we need to feel heard and we need
to be
deeply in touch with you know that
belief
is one of i i i don't want anybody to go
through grief i'm not some sort of
masochist
but there is nothing that humanizes us
more
than growing through grief yeah and one
of the wisest people i met in my life
perhaps
wisest he gave me this advice he said
don't get involved with anybody like he
meant deeply friendship or romantically
who hasn't experienced grief think about
that like at the opposite of the
buddha's story yeah
yeah they will not have they will not
have sunk roots into the depths of their
humanity
that have not gone through grief totally
exactly that
it's it's it's what we're ultimately the
only
thing is to be connected with people
who can afford us the only way we can go
through grief
which is to grow into yeah somebody else
yeah living in another world because
that's what we have to do because
somebody when we lose or somebody dies
our world is destroyed
yeah we have to grow into another person
in another world that's the only way
right and that process that that puts us
in touch
with our humanity and our personality
absolutely
and then it's kind of like when we go
through that there's a sense in which
when we sit with another because i was
thinking about this back to this thing
about with attunement
right of that it's and i think this is
kind of also
what we're you know in dialogue says we
we have two we are tuned by and a tune
into
right these virtues right yes right yes
there's a there's a way in which
when i'm for example when i'm sitting
with somebody with grief
there's so like like there's attuning to
them there's like kind of feeling what
it would be like to be them
and like sensing it and like tuning into
it
but not in a way that's trying to
explore no this is but here's the
here's the thing yeah here's the thing
where i think that that the the practice
of what it
like dialogues the machinery of
exercises
is that like i think real attunement
though is like
yeah i'm attuning into your grief right
but i'm also a tuning in to something
that you may not be able to be
have access in because you're grief
right which is i can
tune into qualities of being i can be
attuned
with you and your grief so i'm like i
can tune into you and i can tune into
your future i can
i can tune into these
and that's like sitting with a wise
person right like
you get the sense yeah that's good
that that that that speaks that puts
into speech sort of an image i had
of when people they need to feel seen
and heard
but your presence i was thinking about
like what can happen is people are
cramped in their green
every long time you ask me what's
different now and i said i'm not stuck
yeah remember that yeah what happens is
you open up this space
you don't say anything to people yeah
there's nothing to say
there's nothing you can say that won't
be useless absolutely useless right but
what you do is
what you just articulated is you open up
a space you scaffold
access right and so that they're they're
not they're not
cramped in their grief they still have
to unfold it and unpack it there's no
way there's not
this is what that wise person said to me
he said there's nothing you can do about
grief except go through it
yeah like that right but what you can do
is like when you're with somebody and
they felt
they feel seen and heard and then you
can
you can like again if you try and do
this in any kind of manipulative fashion
it's it it turns into vice very very
quickly
yeah like totally if you can do it
virtuously
you can open up a space so the person
you're not alleviating their grief
what you're doing is preventing the
grief from being cramped into a kind of
stuckness
yeah yes yes yes
absolutely and there's a way that you
just think about it you know it's just
kind of like just imagine grieving right
with yoda
right there's a sense where he would not
look away he would not diminish
he wouldn't deny he in fact if anything
he'll
he'll uncomfortably reflect back to you
how painful it is
in all of its dimensions maybe even more
than you're feeling it
but at the same time he's also probably
revealing eternity to you at this at
everything beyond it right there's that
sense of i really like this sense of
attunement
and attuning into things and what's
happening in and also
with speech and thought right like
hearing
right all these things kind of working
together
and this sense of you know there's
always that sense of
of where you know when the geist
that we've been tuning into right
at some point shows up as the thing is
is is the thing that was always already
the case
yes yes like there's that that quality
of at some point
the the always already becomes
like think of what you're inside of yeah
but this is the platonic insight about
that
that feature of the logos which you know
one of the things i love about you is
you
always you always give voice to that you
always call us back to this
and you always wonder about this like
comment
do reverence about it but think about
this was plato's point and this is part
of the anamnesis idea
right is that virtues have to have that
to them to some degree if you have no
and this was part of aristotle's worry
about education and why you have to have
the right parents but if you have no
uh if you have if you do not have the
power if you do not have
uh the potency in act right the actual
potentiality
activated the power right if you don't
have some honesty
i can't teach you honestly right i can't
right if you don't have that commitment
if you don't sense it's normativity
yeah like there's no way there's no
right yeah yeah that you you maybe you
think about the grief
you may be i'm thinking of socrates
right you may be cramped
you may be stuck right and i can afford
you
unfolding that but if there's a sense in
which it's anamnesis
like you always had to have some genuine
virtue of honesty that's why you can
exemplify it
in the practice and then be called by it
right
the virtue is where we where we can
really pick up on we can really and i
need this work very strongly now
where we can personalize that feature
that you keep putting your finger on
that we discover we come to discover
something
that is already something we prep
present
and affording us i come to discover what
honesty is only because
there was some honesty in you and i
already there affording the discussion
of honesty
right right interesting
so so yeah so interesting i just want to
kind of hang with that for a second
he had that sense of that that sense of
that always already right
it is
when it reveals itself right
there's a sense like this is where like
things like faith
and trust seem to
seem to be something just indigenous to
it
right i agree there's something about
there's something about like
there's something about like finding
fine like that there's that experience
of like
you know you just think you're fucked
right you just think it's
like you're in some kind of catastrophic
thing and it's like you're just
convinced it's all going to fall apart
and then at some point something happens
or you realize or somebody says
something and all of a sudden you're
like
whoop you're like oh it's it's fine
in fact it was fine the whole time right
and there's that sense in which like
where it's been okay
in this way that i didn't i couldn't
produce it like out of nothing
there's something about that recognition
of the
background it's already always already
been
in there and it i could like that i
could it could be concealed for me
and it still operate and organize
the experience and be present without
like in a certain sense
without me yes right
even maybe in spite of me on some level
right that there's there's some kind of
sense of
because there's that quality there's
that quality of um
like i'm thinking about when like the
quality of of
of awareness or being or the felt sense
of what wink
talks about the um the holding
environment yeah yeah
yeah right yeah because on some level i
think
i think that there's a way in which
we're always tuned into a certain way
because we're always inside of something
we're always in the world so there's
always this
the way it seems or it is and there's
a quality of like holdedness right
and so there's something about there's
something about these kinds of dialogues
right that are so encouraging
right yes right by the way
totally it's like they're encouraging
and i think
the faith part is this kind of
recognition of
oh god there's just like there's
something there's an intelligibility
that's beyond me it's operating through
me
and i can it can be concealed for me and
it still goes
right and then when i find out if
there's something about that just goes
really deep
in the nervous system i i think i think
your point about how that engenders
virtues like courage it encourages us
i think it entrusts us very trust us
um and you know it you know it brings us
into
you know a kind of faithfulness i think
that's deeply right yeah
notice again come back to the you know
the point that gonzalez makes
notice how the way you could be mistaken
about this
that which was that which i discovered
but was which was always there
you could mistake that with the the the
untutored intuition of common sense you
could oh it's just my intuition
it's not that it's not that or you could
mistake that with oh well there's a
there's a there's a there's a definition
that captures this
and i can then hold on to it by holding
on to the definition
you can't hold faith is not holding on
to
a dogma or a definition nor is it just
your untutored intuition see how both of
those
are mistakes of we're trying to talk
about something that's neither just
intuition nor formalized possession
right because yes you said you
discovered that
it was always there but it's also with
real discovery that's why i like this
term inventio
yes right between discovery and
invention right right
right right and it's not your possession
you don't
right so but again there's a virtue here
of getting that
sensitivity to that sweet spot where
you're stealing between
the skill and corruptness of you know
the obviousness of my intuition and
common sense
or you know the self-evidence of this
formal definition
capture everything completely and
consistently
defined right you know it's you're
trying to find and that's what you see
the dialogues doing again and again and
again
sail between those sail between those
sail between those
right totally and fi and then
and then finding in finding that
you like that sense i know jordan does
this a lot right where he'll be like
he'll like he'll recognize oh wait a
minute i realized
when like this maybe it got too fast or
something like that like when it went
off
that i was tuning in there was a flow
that was happening that didn't reveal
itself until it was gone
right and then what is that that sense
of finding
all of our attention being oriented to
something right
i think so i think it's about i think
it's
it's all of these things it's a sense of
an emerging
right relationship the connectedness
that sense that we
are being we are being educated in the
sense of a deuce draw forth
that i'm cramping and unfolding of
virtue but but that virtue is always
bound up with this necessarily with the
way in which
right the the speaking that is thinking
of the logos is becoming beautiful to us
and drawing us and saying
look and you're going oh yes this is
what this is what i could be
oh yeah this is this is well that's that
that
there's there's like the hermenetic
circle yeah right that sense of that
sense of
of yeah there's that sense of as i step
forward right that what i was stepping
on
like goes in the background but then
becomes in front of me
yeah in that auto poetic yeah it's viral
right that's a fantastic connection yeah
exactly
exactly and so so hermes the messenger
god
language right yep totally
totally between the two right dude
always moving between the two
yeah so good this is so much fun
[Laughter]
this is so much fun thank you john well
thank you god
it's like i mean it's this
sorry i i don't want this to sound
self-congratulatory
but i want to say i'm trying to express
reverence and not be
self-congratulatory but this is
this is this kind of stuff yeah and then
you know and then the work i'm doing
with you
and peter and jordan i you know
you know chris right and like trying to
uh you know
theorize about it but never to lose
touch with the theory
or now the theorgia right and trying to
get them
all like that's the most important thing
i'm doing
that is the most important thing i'm
doing yes right it is it is what jordan
said it would be he foresaw that and as
this gets worked out it becomes you know
the meta psycho technology
that shepherds and curates and
coordinates
it feed it feeds from but it also really
feeds back into all of the other
practices
i practice and teach and try to share
with people
it's becoming so important to me yeah
it's like it's gathering i get this
sense of
and i've been watching this with you
i've been watching this with you because
when i first when we first talked i
don't think
the sense of dialogues was articulated
yet in fact you were
i think you were i watched one of your
one of your first videos with
chris when you were doing the series
yeah in fact you're like yeah i'm trying
to work this thing out like that there's
something
yeah yeah right if you were talking
about it in terms of like the role of
religion
right and like okay traditionally
religion has taken this that's become
less and less viable so how is it that
we get these things together is so
interesting because it
you could tell you were like it was
present
as the struggle of its missing
right oh yeah totally um
hang on one second i just my my neighbor
i have to close my door hang on
i got a little bit too socratically
inspired by
for my neighbor's case
[Laughter]
but that sense of um
you know that's uh there was just that
sense of it
you were aware and then it seems like
dialogues
right and in this thing just went oh
like everything's just started to come
together and i'm getting this sense of
everything seems to be gathering itself
like and there's the logo
right the the gathering of the logos
in the face like really picking up all
that in the face of the kairos
that this is what is singing to me right
now most
pressingly but also beautifully yeah
yeah
like that's exactly and in that moment
where jordan said that to me
right so i had very good i mean good
faith criticisms
by jonathan pagio and paul
and then when jordan said that and then
i had that moment of coming to something
that responded to them and but i
couldn't have done any of it on my own
it had to be like it was with
and through him and then you know and
then i started you know i was already in
dialogue with you
yeah yeah just started and i'm starting
to see this unfolding
that's when it all came together and i
realized ah this
this is this is it that was that was you
know that that was
that that was the touchstone right that
started to reveal uh you know
when he said yeah when he said the
medici the medici
technology of yeah they take yeah the
better technology
and then you're like the next day you're
like i think the thing that's circling
maybe the thing that did it and then
that's been
the conversation that going and more and
more people now are spontaneously
this is this is how you can tell where i
think you're really starting to get
something
uh is more and more people are starting
to
see how these things could uh you know
how they could instantiate and exemplify
and afford
a religion that's not a religion so more
and more people are saying i'm getting a
sense
like you just did about and again i'm
not the author of this
yeah i'm not a founder that's a
ridiculous idea but the
the sense right uh like yeah i'm getting
a sense of what this could be
like it's now it's gone from being an
abstract
proposition or just some image
it's going to be no no no this this is
this is like
this is actually nascent there is
something that is
coming to birth right now and and so
that
that for me is like okay i i stopped and
i made very careful attention the same
thing i do with like
teaching my students when they start to
oh
right they start to get the gathering
like you say right and
it starts to take on a life of its own
that's when it's like oh yeah yeah
yeah yeah i think you're exactly right
this is this is what is so
exciting about right now
and and again how to do this virtually
how to
be how to be properly in relationship
with this excitement and this creativity
without losing touch with the suffering
and the distress
they're happening and how to keep them
like in
in in in proper proportion yeah that's
what ratio eventually
right rakio was the latin of logos right
but
it was trying to the proper
proportioning was that how they tried to
get the sense of
yeah that to me is something again i'm
trying to get like
how do we how do we do that that kinship
and that friendship with the logos yes
like i was thinking about like
in a certain sense you know how like
aristotle would talk about like that the
that we think with the logos right
like that that like it's we think with
it right
but then there's a certain point where
it's like you think with it
but then at some point like it kind of
like the logos almost takes over
right it's through you yeah and there's
a there's a point where the logos
thinks logos right well yeah
and for me and that's where the musical
metaphors from taoism are more
really helpful because initially you're
listening to the music and then you
start to pick it up
but then what starts to happen is
instead of you just sort of listening to
the music
it's almost like you start to become yet
another instrument
right um in in the orchestra right you
get orchestrated
by the music like just any other
instrument it goes back to your tuning
metaphor
yeah right yeah absolutely absolutely
and that sense
too of you know oh and kind of going
back to the like towards the beginning
of our conversation just bringing in
that whole thing about
just wondering about this like and i
don't know if i understand his
model completely but that whole thing
about the justification what was what
did he call that
when it comes out that your friend where
it comes out of his out of
so he i mean he originally talked about
it as the justification hypothesis
but then he moved into sort of a
justification system it's great on reeks
i really recommend people check out uh
that discussion with him
that was he is really i really like he's
he's his ability to think really clearly
right about and just take all of these
things he's just really
i really i want to i want to speak with
him
well you should yeah yeah i mean
he's going to be on the i think he's
been on the discord server my discord
server
uh like i said he greg and i are going
to do
he uh um he's been sort of following all
the
stuff i'm doing on consciousness right
now um
and so he and i are gonna have another
discussion
and we're going to do it about sort of
consciousness the problem of
consciousness
but we're going to try and circle
through his work and mine
he sees he sees
he sees really deep connections uh with
you know the the tree of knowledge that
that he's been working on
the attempt to get a synoptic
integration yeah of psychology
and and the work i'm doing on relevance
realization the synoptic integration and
cognitive science
what's happening is that well it's
reciprocal opening between his work and
i
yeah but yeah
he uh i mean there's been a a later book
by sperm wilson
um no not suburban wilson my mistakes
berber and mercier called
the enigma of reason where they
basically argue for
um that reason is properly
is properly a property and process
within distributed cognition it's
dialogical not monological in nature
big tone of a book the thing of it is
uh greg uh i mean
there's been a dispute between them
right
but it's clear to my mind after looking
at both
greg has absolute precedent he published
way before they did
his argument it almost everything that
they have in their argument he has
in his right i think the way to think
about it is
i don't think they stole from him at
least i don't i don't have any good
reason for saying that
i think they should properly give him
academic precedence that's what you
should do
yeah sort of held off on that i'm not
happy with that
but what you've got is you've got two
and the similarities are so telling
you've got this powerful convergence of
all of this work being integrated
independently and then converging on
this idea
and greg deserves real like credit for
this
i'm not trying to take away from sperver
and mercy but greg really deserves
credit for this
you know for that you know reason is
ultimately dialogical in nature yeah
yeah totally in this sense of
the sense of the justification yes right
the forum of justification no other
animal justifies
we are persons precisely because
we justify and here's the thing the
justification is always bi-directional
we are always justifying to others
and justifying to ourselves justifying
ourselves to others but we're also
justifying others to us
right trust who is worthy
yeah i trust right totally now here's
the thing about that is that
like there's a way no wonder what i
thought what i thought when i heard that
i was like well no wonder people get
nervous when they make eye contact
right like there's this phenom i think
that's what levanos really pointed out
kind of phenomenal
logically it was like why is the human
face always confront me as an enigma but
there's a sense in which that sense of
obligation
yes i wonder if the obligation is the
obligation and responsibility of
justification on some level of like
and what also he said the thing about
the reverse engineering
of being able to speak i thought was a
great way of putting it
of like oh yeah yeah well he and i have
been you know
talking about that and and you know
that's the met i told him you know the
design stance is the method
the methodology of cognitive science
engineering
i mean this is what you and i are trying
to do here we're trying to reverse
engineer
uh dialectic right yeah from the
historical sources and the current
practices
yeah you know and yeah greg was very
much doing that
i mean there's something weird right
because when
when it's it it's
right because animals have something
they have
like if they're facing each other
there's there's there's threat
either a social threat of dominance or
threat of predation
right or or even just confrontation for
sexual competition
right so there's animal threat you there
but then as you said
and lebanon points out there's this
existential ethical
because we're persons in the space of
reason and justification
there's this extra thing that comes on
top of it and there's there
and and then we and what's really
problematic is not only are both
happening we confuse them
and like and we equivocate and we get
messed up about those two different
things
yeah right very very hard you know i've
heard this i've heard people reliably
say
and apparently and there's there's
there's there's surveys and polls to
support this
that the fear of speaking in front of
others
is greater than their fear of death yes
right
right exactly because they could die
their personhood
is is on trial yes exactly exactly
and so there's so this is what's really
interesting is like
a couple of things to look at in the
context of that
right of one
it seems like so so there's there's
really toxic versions of that
right there's toxic versions of that
thing going on right and that's
that experience of shame and humiliation
and having to prove yourself and you and
you have to hide it
or you have to be your justification is
defensive
right in some way like it's like being
in the courtroom
um but i'm just wondering about it's
interesting to think about is like
well
from the courtroom to the courtyard that
sort of metaphor that's in my mind
yeah from the courtroom to the courtyard
yes exactly
exactly so what's interesting is like
what is it
when you make that move right
if we what is the l or like that you
could say the elevation of that
structure
right what is it that's getting
justified or maybe it's like the
experience of
justice right yeah but i think that's it
i think instead of the project uh
of justifying ourselves right
i i'm going to play with that word a
little because seriously logos right
yeah don't know how when you justify the
text
where you're right or left justification
you try to come into right relationship
so that intelligibility is maximized
yeah so
i think of it like this is a metaphor
that the justification we're pursuing
is not the inferential defense of our
proposition yes it's again the proper
alignment
it's coming into the right relationship
totally people are oriented for that
what happens is i go from the
the attack mode because i've been
thinking about this
for the rebel wisdom thing on saturday i
go from attack to an amplification
right if there's something so the way i
challenge you
think about in order for them to be flow
i have to challenge you
yeah like is it just oh i agree with you
we all love each other and isn't this
wonderful and let's see granola
it's not that crap right i have to
challenge you because if i don't put a
demand on you
first of all you don't have to respond
and secondly you won't get into the flow
state there's no flow state without
demand
but if i attack you right then we're
into the courtroom
but if i move to amplification where i
say well you're talking about
courage and i hear you first of all i
acknowledge i make sure that i resonate
with you
i commit to the process not the
proposition
and then after that i say but there's
something about courage that i love
there's an aspect that i didn't hear in
what you're saying yeah and what do you
think about this
what do you think about this and i try
to get you right right unpack
i heard you saying this is this right is
there more here you do this guy yeah and
then what you'll do is you first
um help me unpack remember the
uncramping what i'm thinking
and then you'll say and we all do this
to each other when we're there
we'll do the amplification we'll say but
there's i'm putting words but we usually
enact it rather than saying it yeah yeah
in words it's like but here's another
thing about courage that i love
that i didn't quite hear and what you
were saying but
but you do it in a jazz way you say
here's here's what i heard
yeah and here's another and can we can
we jazz our way from the one
to the other can we find the connecting
flow
right so we turn this is what i mean
about moving from
the courtroom into the courtyard we
challenge but the challenge is not the
challenge of attack
the challenge is the challenge of
amplification yeah i try
i acknowledge the suchness of what you
said i acknowledge
in what you've said what i have not yet
seen
but then i challenge you with the
moreness of what
you might not have yet seen right and
together
stereoscopically we come to see
something more than we could see before
both of us together is both the ground
and the aspiration
yes yes exactly exactly right totally
oh interesting yeah interesting and that
starts to get into
like where whereas normally like in a
courtroom
it's all about like stress it's it's
like there's
there's something that you're trying to
like win and avoid
and it's establish a position yeah yeah
it's positional
right exactly right but this is
processional yeah if the one of the
things i'm going to ask people like when
you ask them to set an intention for
alexio
you can say set the intention for
reverence yeah transformation and a
commitment to the process
rather than to any position right and
not attack
what we do is we acknowledge we amplify
and then we anticipate right we're
anticipating getting to somewhere we
couldn't get to
these are the things that i this is what
i'm trying this is what i'm going to
bring into
the presentation on saturdays
this is what i want to then get feedback
on and circle it back in
when you and i when the four of us
regularly keep
trying to reverse engineer dialectics
right
absolutely beautiful and i have a client
as a matter of fact
this is a great place to complete that's
a great place
so yes please remember to send me this
deep reference my friend
yeah yeah deep send me the file i'm
going to upload
you upload it first on your channel okay
i'll upload it on voices with for vaki
and then hopefully you'll get on the
discord server right away
okay great what what what should we call
this one you think
um i yeah
yeah what was coming out here was
i i think what was coming out here is
virtue in dialogues
both senses the virtue in the via logos
and how virtue
induces virtue how dialogue this induces
virtue from us
and the virtue that is drawn forth from
us bingo all right
oh take care my friend this is wonderful
this is awesome i've missed you yeah yes
i miss you so much yeah goodbye